AI is easily the greatest discovery
humanity will ever make.
>> This is not an easy game to win or to
start, but this is not going to be
stopped.
>> AI is sucking up all of the liquidity
and it's causing a problem in crypto.
And now, oh Jesus, we're 2008 again.
>> This has cost more opportunity cost than
anything I've ever seen.
>> Meanwhile, the dollar keeps going up and
they all say, "Yeah, but it's going to
crash."
>> Every empire that's ever had a reserve
currency has lost it.
>> What useful information is that?
How useful How useful is it? How does
that help anybody apart from create a
long doomy story about the world so the
US has lost its empire, the dollar is
over, it's all going to collapse. How
does that help anybody? Who do you think
is going to be running economies in 10
years time?
It's obviously going to be AI.
>> What I see happening in crypto shows
that AI, a good thing, can pull
liquidity out of the system so
profoundly that somebody that was in
crypto on debt now finds themselves in
trouble. If we get a bearish sentiment
that ends up hitting
let's just round it to the eurodollar.
And people just suddenly start going,
"Nah, I don't want to lend money
anymore." To whatever. And now, oh
Jesus, we like we're 2008 again.
>> But
Tom, let's just call it a business
cycle.
Happens all the time.
It's exactly That's what it's supposed
to do.
>> So you know something like that's
probably going to happen, but just don't
be a dumbass.
>> It's very clear to me by 2030 we have no
clue how the world's going to work
really.
We just we don't.
>> That's the economic singularity.
>> Yeah, we just don't at that point. What
does it mean when you put an AGI brain
into a robot?
You know,
what does it mean when GDP growth can go
at 20%? Who does it accrue to, as you
say?
To the invisible economy of agents we
can never see, we can never touch, we
can't talk to. That's a wild world,
right? So, I I've been saying, you know,
all along, I've been very consistent, is
this period is pretty easy.
We've got them
the exponential age of technology
kicking in
furiously, which I started talking about
about
5, 6 years ago. And we're like, we've
never seen anything like this. And to
your point, the Central Bank has to keep
debating currency, so our investments go
up,
regardless. And we're in a race with
China that we cannot lose, simply cannot
lose. It's humanity level stakes.
And China will say the same thing, they
cannot lose the US cuz no, we can't have
a world system run by one AI.
Can't happen.
So, therefore, the chances and we got
the CapEx spend,
the biggest in history, planned out by
companies with huge amounts of money.
So, the chances are this elongates for a
bit.
Now, the
problem with it elongating
is you end up with more ex- excesses.
Because not everybody's great, right?
You end up with
people misvaluing all sorts of shares,
all sorts of things, things can go bust,
whatever. I just don't think it's now. I
just don't think it's now, you know? Um
and then I don't know what the world
looks like in 2030. What is a company?
What is a corporation? It's to give a
a group of people together
the rights of a human, which is what's
corporate, so it has the legal rights
and status,
and it exists to make a profit. I don't
know, it's a weird concept actually, the
bunch of humans
working for this entity that is no
thing.
Like, what is
Royal Dutch Shell, one of the biggest
oil companies in the world? Nobody knows
anymore what it is. It's just a thing
that just does its thing.
No reason that can't be an automated
thing doing its thing. So, what is the
value of half of these companies? We
don't know. What could the stock market
do in 2032?
Well, you know, SpaceX could be worth
$10 trillion and
and 80% of the US companies could fail.
And the economy could still grow.
It's like it's a really weird world,
Tom, and and I don't know what it means.
And so, I just think
I'm not going to worry about that yet.
I'll worry about trying to
protect yourself by making as much money
as possible in the interim.
Um and make intelligent decisions by
using it as an opportunity to not have
that.
To be able to observe
rather than freak out what it's going to
do to me.
You can observe and say, I wonder how
this is going to play out. It's a much
easier mindset to go through if you've
kind of planned for it. And this is
exactly what I've been talking about.
You know, when I started, I said, you
have 6 years to unfuck your future, then
5 years to unfuck your future. We've got
about 4 years
to get this right. The gift of the
opportunity was there. I mean,
technology, we're crypto before it. Now
we've got technology, crypto probably
have another one.
It's all there. Just invest in your own
demise. Don't fear the demise.
>> Wow.
>> you if you always think
that tomorrow's going to be a rainy day,
you never go out anywhere. Or today, you
know, you just
And it stops you investing.
And that's what I've I learned the hard
way that I always looked for the doom.
And what I did was miss the upside.
And not over short periods of time, but
I I still see it with friends of mine.
The kind of gold bugs who've been doing
this doom-mongering
for 30 years.
And they've not made money
because they haven't been able to
invest. They've kept their capital
You know, they they've they've staved
off devaluation and and um debasement by
owning gold, let's say.
But they've missed the entire output of
humanity, which is this increasing in
intelligence. They hated it because it
was always going to go bust.
But that's mad.
When human ingenuity
and the rise of intelligence and the
increase in the value of Nasdaq
companies or technology companies
overall is relentless.
The technology companies of the past
you know, get replaced by new technology
companies. So, yeah, could you be in the
wrong company? You just buy the Nasdaq.
It's the same thing with the crypto.
Always buy Bitcoin, buy Nasdaq
and
save up some cash and if there's a big
sell-off when it's down 50%
you say thank you very much and buy some
more.
>> How does somebody avoid the um reality
that when the dot-com bust happened um
it took 15 to 20 years for a lot of
those companies to rebound.
>> So, you're missing what I'm saying.
Let's say price of asset peak is 100.
Let's say you got in at
the last part of it. So, you got in at
70 or 80, let's say, right? So, you
didn't get the absolute top
and it falls 90%. So, it's down to 10.
>> Yep.
>> And you double your position. Your
average is now 50.
Where did it How long did it take to
clear that? Not very long at all.
If you chose
a bit of stock picking, had you chosen
Amazon into that fall, which had been
down 96%?
I mean, Christ.
The amount of money you would made, you
would more than compensated for that
sell-off that you had.
But people just think so short term.
Because what they're not doing is
projecting their future self.
Here, you're projecting your current
self onto your future.
So, if you're saying, "Hey, there's a
secular trend that goes probably into
infinity and there'll be some big ups
and downs on route and I'll take
advantage of those by if it gets wildly
overpriced, I might sell some and if it
gets
back down to super cheap levels, I'll
just buy more.
But most people actually fear going
there
because they're worried there's a
pothole in the road.
It's like
I say I don't get it. Of course I get it
because the human emotion side is the
hardest part and I've been there. I've
been paralyzed by that stuff in the
past.
I I was paralyzed from 2008 to really
buy equities after 2008.
I just didn't buy equities. It took me
until
to buy equities again.
Yeah.
I mean I made money in all sorts of bond
markets and currency markets and stuff,
but equities, no way.
And in fact, I would I saw 2000 coming
because I saw this demographic bust
coming as well. So I hadn't been long
equities
myself personally since 1997.
>> So wait, this seems like you're um now
I'm I'm having to update my mental
model. I thought you were saying you're
in equities, they drop, no worries,
double your position, you lower your um
you know, the rate at which you're going
to break even, but you're saying your
actual reaction to 2000 2008 was to
eject out of equities for a very
extended period of time.
>> Yeah, cuz I was lucky enough to be able
to make money in other things, right?
Cuz I'm a
a a macro
investor.
But that's the psychological scarring
that you do.
And if I'd have just held on to the S&P
500, which is not the most exciting
thing in the world, since 1997,
it would have made an preposterous
amount of money. And this was the same
lesson I learned with Bitcoin if you
remember. Told you that story where I
sold out and blah blah blah and then
bought back in and I've realized why is
Jeff Bezos so rich? Why is Warren
Buffett so rich? Why is all of this
stuff so? It's because they basically
have long-term holds and they buy when
it's cheap.
And you started with Buffett here and
Buffett's wildly underperformed a lot of
people, lot of stocks over time, but
really all he's doing
he just holds on to stocks for a very
long time and if they get cheap, he buys
some more. This is exactly what I'm
saying. But because I quite like racier
things that go up faster
because it's not other people's capital,
it's my capital.
>> Mhm.
>> That's That's different.
>> If we were going to run an average Joe
playbook right now, I think I've heard
you just say it, which is okay, listen,
if I were going to redo
2000 to now, instead of dipping out and
just being gone forever,
I'm not going in on debt, I'm going to
have a broad-based position, I'm going
to think long-term, when things dip
down, then I need to
get back in, not necessarily double my
position, but I need to get back in,
stay in as long as whatever thesis I
believe about the technology, which you
haven't said this here, but you've
very much on record as saying, look,
tech is the only thing that really
grows.
So, presumably that would be the the
statement that the average Joe, you've
got to be in technology in a smart way,
meaning
no debt,
broad-based, and then hold for a long
period of time. Is that the average Joe
playbook?
>> Yeah, and then you think, okay,
how much does it psychologically affect
me
if it goes down?
And
people tell you they're okay with a 50%
drawdown, but they're not.
Um but technology stocks cuz they
perform so much and crypto
because it performs so much over time
has these drawdowns.
So, you have to be honest with yourself,
look yourself in the mirror
and say
50% drawdown.
So, then say, "Okay, my whole investment
pie is
$1,000.
If it went down 50%, how would I feel?
Sick. Okay.
Then, all you do is say, "Okay, I'll
take that portion out in cash.
So, I've reduced my position size.
Now, how do I feel if my
$600 falls 50%? I've lost $300. I don't
mind anymore.
That's your comfort zone. That cash is
what you use when the market falls.
>> Mhm.
>> That's what Buffett is doing. That's all
it is. That's the whole game of
long-term investing. It's so easy, it's
ridiculous, but we complicate it. We
want to go on Excel all day and look for
the latest stock pick, and then we want
to
worry about, you know, where the latest
crash is going to come from. We debate
it and do it. You don't actually need to
do any of that stuff.
>> Okay, I was going to ask you if there
was a metric that if it moved in the
wrong direction, you would consider AI
to be in trouble, bearish territory,
whatever, but it sounds like you don't
really think about that.
>> Of course, I do, cuz I have, you know, I
write research and I have to think about
other people, and we, you know, just
because I
have said to you with conviction, "These
are my views."
You have to hold them loosely because,
you know, nobody knows. Things change.
Things happen. So, I've actually built
myself, I'm going to boast now, with
Claude code, an enormous dash not
dashboard, it's a platform for
Global Macro Investor, my research
business, and then Real Vision as well
has versions of these, but I've built
ones around
just this.
Supercycle, is it going to be a
supercycle? What is the What is the
intelligence cycle?
Where is the debt risk? Where is this?
So, I've got like
15 indications in that that I put
together as one single indicator, and
that's everything from credit spreads on
Oracle and Coe even the other listed
ones to
the rate of change of the earnings of
the hyperscalers through sort of you
know the
rate of change of the adoption of the
technology through to you know there's a
whole bunch of these things that make
sense. You want to see
is that stable? It's of course it's
going to go up and down or something
happening there that's not good. Then we
go back to the so that's the exponential
age stuff. Then we go back to the basics
is is liquidity going up or not? Are
financial conditions amenable for this
to continue? Because to your point
if there is not enough liquidity for the
needs of this beast
then we run into problems.
Because there's not enough money around.
Now what the US has done Kevin Warsh has
done this
um well he he was part of it Scott
Bessent was part of it and Stephen
Miller was part of it. They changed the
banking laws.
And Japan has done the same thing as
well.
What they're doing is
from 2008 until last year
basically all liquidity was provided by
the Treasury or the Federal Reserve.
By the balance sheets and the Treasury
general account and the repo markets and
all this stuff centrally controlled.
What's happened is they're changing the
banking regulations
to make sure the banks do it. So the
banks only two places can two people can
create liquidity. The central bank
it's uh can create money the central
bank or the banking system itself.
And they're basically asking the banking
system to do it. Japan did this
they steepened the yield curve they
released the currency valve and what's
happened is everyone's like oh my god
Japan's going to blow up. The opposite
happened. Japanese banks started
lending.
Why are they doing this? Because it's
exactly your point. There is no way the
governments can provide the liquidity
for this.
So, it has to come from the banking
system, the lending markets, the capital
markets, the savings pools, all of that.
And in the end,
maybe you're right.
In 7 years time, 5 years time, will that
be a misallocation of capital? Doesn't
look like it cuz this is the fastest
growth of anything we've seen.
>> Mhm.
>> But who knows where that ends up and who
does the stupid things cuz there will be
stupid things.
We're seeing margin debt
uh on US equities
as a percentage of market cap
being high already.
And that's like, you know, you don't
like to see that cuz it tells you that
humans are speculating on all of this
stuff.
>> Mhm.
>> You know, you get that stuff. So, but
again, is it likely to end? I mean,
again, I've been through the '90s and
this ain't nothing yet.
It was insane squared. I mean, I I
remember being on holiday, I can't
remember where it was, somewhere in the
Caribbean, some fancy place. Like, no,
it wasn't the Caribbean. I can't
remember where it was. Somewhere in the
world, some very fancy dive resort,
Maldives or somewhere. And I was
chatting to this American guy, I'm like,
"What are you doing here?" He was a guy
who climbed the telegraph poles and
fixed the the AT&T wires.
And he's like, "You know, I've just I
was talking about his new $200,000
kitchen he just put into his house or
whatever the $100,000 whatever the
number was, it was a stupid number. Blah
blah blah." And I'm like, "What do you
do?" And he was the
And I'm like, "How did you do this?" He
goes, "I'm a day trader. It's where I
make all my money." And it's at that
point when you We haven't got there yet.
>> Yeah.
>> We're not We're just not there yet.
>> We'll get right back to the show, but
first, let's talk about an assumption
that virtually all founders make. You
think your company is secure. You've got
people to handle it, but nobody has
necessarily verified it, and that's
where your strategy breaks down. That's
just hope. Horizon 3 ends the guessing
game. Node Zero is an autonomous AI
hacker that actually attacks your own
environment the way a real attacker
would, your entire attack surface,
external to cloud to identity in a
single test. It runs 225,000
production safe tests with zero
downtime. See exactly what an attacker
would find in your environment before
they find it for you. Go to
horizon3.ai/impacttheory
and request your free node zero demo.
Visit horizon3.ai/impacttheory.
Again, that's horizon3.ai/impacttheory.
No commitment is required. Results in
hours, not weeks. Now, let's get back to
the show.
>> What lesson should we be taking right
now is where crypto's at in this moment,
which I'll say is chopping sideways.
Is that a liquidity story? AI's just
sucked all the enthusiasm and all the
money or is it a fundamentally flawed
tech that nobody's going to remember?
>> No, I mean, look, it's exactly
exactly as you said. There's a certain
amount of liquidity.
And the reason being is the US is not
making a lot of it because what they
want is the banking system to do it.
But the yield curve is because of the
Iran war and slightly pernicious
inflation and the oil price and stuff
like that, the yield curve's not been
steep, so banks aren't kind of wanting
to lend at the long end. They're not
making enough turn, enough spread.
So, that's stopped the banks using their
balance sheets enough yet.
So, wash, they're they're trying to get
that resolved.
That's That those are the levers they
want.
Um and then the banking system should
step in, but generally speaking, US
liquidity growth has not been big.
And that's been the reason.
So, if it's not growing super fast, my
general um broad liquidity measure is
about 4%, but we need to grow it about
8% to fund the debts
and the interest payments. So therefore
it is enough to fund the AI bet but it's
not enough to fund everything else.
>> Mhm.
>> And they have to do something about it
cuz the interest payments on the debt
they've got a lot of debt to roll this
year.
So
>> Yeah and they keep jamming at the short
end which is liquidity. So yeah
liquidity is not enough yet versus what
we need for this. They're hoping the
banking system takes the difference.
Then crypto takes off.
I think it all resolves itself.
Again they're not
They're not stupid. I always take I've
known Scott Bessent for 30 years.
I first went into his office when he was
at Soros and I was at Goldman Sachs in
London. He's been to my house in Spain.
He was a subscriber to my research for
many years.
>> Let's go.
>> So
he's not a stupid guy. These guys know
what they're doing. Now do they get it
right?
Different matter but they know the game.
Don't forget we've got a macro hedge
fund manager running the US Treasury.
Never happened before.
And we know
we know we
we understand his language. He
understands our language. He knows the
game.
>> Yeah no doubt Bessent is an interesting
character to me.
I think he's becoming more political as
the days go by but yeah it definitely
feels like you've got somebody that
understands how to pull the levers in
the right way.
So as you look at where crypto goes do
you think that people are going to
return to it because there is something
fundamental there? Like when I look at
the Clarity Act and I see Japan moving
on there as I see Russia moving on there
as
you know I get how it creates appetite
for debt. You get the stable coins back
at one to one. The US started the hype
train on that, but we haven't been able
to get it across the finish line. Do you
think it's That finally goes across the
finish line, we've got a fundamental
reason why people come back? Um or is it
just No, no, no. Crypto is when there's
enough liquidity slashing around, people
go way out on the risk curve. Crypto's a
fun thing that they can gamble on.
>> Um all of the above.
I mean, you know, we can't pretend that
it's not the most liquidity sensitive
asset on Earth. Reason being, it's the
scarcity in Bitcoin, and then Bitcoin
drives further speculation, it goes out
the risk curve. But it's also a
technology.
And that's the important part to
understand. Let's use Ethereum cuz it's
easy, or Solana. These are just
technologies.
They're technologies that allow you to
do certain things.
And what we're seeing, finally, is the
entire financial system scrambling to
adopt it.
So, it's not just about buying Ethereum.
In fact, they don't really care about
that stuff. Sure, some investors do.
What they care about is using
blockchain. And Ethereum is the cost of
the block space.
It's a currency in that respect. It's a
claim on the block space.
And so, we're seeing the rise of stable
coins. It's been huge how fast they're
growing.
And everybody's built from Stripe to
Shopify to Circle to I mean, you name
it. Everybody's building out stable
coins. So, they've made the decision.
Scott Bessent has said, "Well, this is
where the liquidity for our debt's going
to come from."
We want to get to
a trillion, two trillion, three trillion
of stable coins. Why? Cuz it means that
US dominance of currency goes to the end
person in the rice field in the
Philippines, where they're holding
dollars in stable coins,
to the fact that three trillion of
stable coins is a three trillion buyer
of short-term debt.
>> Mhm.
>> Great. That solves a bit a lot of
problems. So, stable coins is good for
everybody, which is why it got through
its regulations super fast. It's an
economic weapon. It's an economic
superpower. Increases velocity of money.
Does all the things you want it to do.
Then the banks are
building
rails for
tokenizing assets.
Funds,
real estate, whatever it is, because
it's an efficient way of doing it.
Great. Then the DTCC who custodies and
clears all of this stuff
does like four quadrillion trades a year
or whatever.
Well, they're building on this now. The
Nasdaq's building on it. So, the use of
the technology
is going like this. But, they're also
relatively early stage. So, the
speculators
are the difference.
So, the the the the building is all
happening.
The speculators are the difference.
Right now, the building is still
relatively early apart from stablecoins
which are growing fast.
A real world assets are growing fast,
but they're too small, and the
speculators aren't around cuz there's
not enough money around. So, you might
as well if you've got any speculating in
these, you trade.
>> Mhm.
>> Probability of the
of the
bull market returning, continuing the
secular trend that it's been in since it
came out, you know, for me is extremely
high because
every single bank and every single
financial institution and every single
government is telling us going to.
They wouldn't be regulating if it's not
going to happen.
The entire banking system is telling us
going to happen. Everybody from Larry
Fink to Jamie Dimon is telling us going
to happen.
And yet people are saying well, it's not
going to happen. So,
that that's highly unlikely. So, it's
the liquidity story more than anything
that brings in excess
capital and excess savings, which allows
us to speculate more, which is why they
always go hand in hand.
Um and I think we haven't got to that
point in markets because liquidity has
not been growing enough.
And my bet is it's coming.
>> Mhm. All right, I've got a crazy idea
that I'm not even sure how much I
believe in this, but it uh certainly is
in the back of my mind that one thing
that's going to happen is you've got the
central banks buying up gold trying to
get out from under the US system, I
think. And China obviously being the
most aggressive among them. I think
China's really making a play to I think
they're going to try to back the Yuan
with gold and say, "No, listen, you guys
have us all wrong. Like we're the
sensible people." But at a minimum,
they're going to be able to get out from
under gold. They've stopped their own
people from trading paper gold.
I think they want to get a Hoover to get
all the gold that they can to leave the
US, the West, London certainly, and get
over into China
both in the central banks and with
personal buying. And then if they ever
need to clamp that valve off, they can
do what the US did and revalue the Yuan
or whatever they decide to do. But
what's interesting to me in terms of
Bitcoin is you've got this major play
where
the number one central bank asset is now
gold over US debt. And I think for a
digital native, we have call it one
generation right now that were kids when
Bitcoin came out. So for them, Bitcoin's
just a thing. You're going to raise
another generation for whom not only
Bitcoin will be that. Bitcoin will be
like the graybeards. That's what they're
into. But stablecoins will just be the
native way that they think about it. And
as the world begins to say, "We need to
get out from under US debt as a reserve
asset. We're going to gold." That the
digital natives will be like, "Oh, yeah,
cool. I want the same idea. I just want
mine in Bitcoin because I don't like the
idea that it's physical. I have to store
it somewhere."
And I could see that cuz I don't think
right now people actually treat Bitcoin
like digital gold. Though for me, that
remains the most compelling aspect of
Bitcoin. Could you see that
psychological shift happening or do you
think that's fairy dust?
>> Until it gets closer to saturation of
its total addressable market
um and volatility goes down
you're not going to it's harder to
substitute
because it's volatile.
So, if you're putting it in your
savings assets, it's quite hard in gold.
I mean, gold can move a reasonable
amount.
You know, 20% correction is not unusual
and they can last years. Uh and in
Bitcoin, it's 50% 60% whatever the
number is, you pick your number. Um so,
until it gets
deeper
more mature
um
it's unlikely to do that, but that
process is the process of getting mature
as more people use it, and more people
adopt it, and more people lock it away,
and less people trade it, and it becomes
less speculative, all of that. So, yeah,
I think that's coming. Um I
Yes.
Many of the world's central banks want
to be less beholden to the US.
Um
but the there's no way they can operate
without them and they're not going to
the system cannot operate without
dollars.
Um
and I've heard from my entire career uh
China or choose your own country is
going to go and back to the gold
Nobody's going to go back to the gold
standard. It's never going to happen.
It's
far too difficult.
>> they're moving so hard then to buying
gold?
>> Well, because their currency's been
going down.
I mean, think of a central bank, right?
Most central banks just do two trades.
When their currency's going down
they buy gold.
When their currency or the US dollar
starts going down
they actually
they buy dollars and treasuries.
They have They run this
almost all of them run this whole
strategy um
as a function of their inflows and
outflows and and exports because when
the US dollar is weak, they're selling
more products.
When the US dollar is weak, the
economy's working better, This
currencies are strong. They're making
money. They start investing in US
assets. And the other way with gold. So,
yeah, over time they want to diversify
assets
for sure.
But I don't think anybody's got an
answer to how do we get away from the
dollar.
>> I don't want to put words in your mouth.
For me, it's just a question of
timeline. Um when I look at what the US
is going to have to do, they're going to
keep inflating. And if I am in a cold
war with the US, which China is in my
estimation, I certainly don't want to be
beholden to them. I want to get as much
strength as I can. I'm already choking
them out from a rare earth metal and
processing standpoint, from a
manufacturing standpoint. Basically, all
drone roads lead through Beijing. So, if
I can also weaken their influence over
me because I hold their debt, I will,
which they obviously are selling the
debt. Um so, while I get it right now,
the system certainly operates on USD and
it's certainly not going to change like
>> Tom Marlo has said this. Luke Grommen
I've heard it from, you know, all of
these people. This argument has been
going on my entire career.
>> Okay, let me ask I'll ask something.
>> Not once has it been true, Tom. Not
once.
>> Well, So, I'm going to make a case that
the it's because you're looking at the
time scale incorrectly. And that these
guys have called the thing that actually
is happening. And so, it's just that
yeah, it might take another 20 years or
whatever, but from a direction of travel
perspective, uh it seems pretty
self-evident that China is is going to
free itself from being beholden to the
US.
Uh that the US has done itself so dirty
from a petrodollar standpoint that
you're going to see a weakening of the
petrodollar. You've already got Scott
Bessent saying we need a Bretton Woods
2.0. So, he admits the petrodollar's not
working anymore. So, it's like, well, if
we're in this state of flux, I think
these guys have been pointing to
something that is I'll say it's an
inevitability. Every empire that's ever
had a reserve currency has lost it on
roughly the timeline that we're on now.
And yeah, it may take a very long time.
So, these guys might have started
calling a 50-year
um move at year 50. And so, now it's
going to take a very long time for that
actually to play out.
>> what useful information is that?
How use How useful is it to say in 50
years' time
the world may have adopted a different
currency based around electricity and
some of them might use gold.
How does that help anybody?
Apart from create a long doomy story
about the world's so [\h__\h] the US has
lost its empire, the dollar is over,
it's all going to collapse. How does
that help anybody? This is why I've got
real issue with this story cuz I've
heard it my whole life and it's it's
actually lost people more money than any
single other mimetic that's ever been
spread. Even more than
>> Interesting.
>> buy these stocks at the top. Anything.
This has cost more opportunity cost than
anything I've ever seen. Meanwhile, the
dollar keeps going up and they all say,
"Yeah, but it's going to crash."
>> Well, that's interesting. So, I'm not
saying it's going to crash. So, I'm
painting a I have a different
>> How can they move away from the Go on.
>> So, the way that I think about this, the
reason I think that it makes sense to
pay attention to that move is
um I come at this from the perspective
of um
don't think that you see the future
clearly, so don't make like these really
extreme bets. Um
given that I see people moving away from
uh the dollar, I think, okay, central
banks are more interested now in holding
gold. So, while I would never want a
meaningful percentage of my portfolio to
be in gold, it's like, oh, cool, that's
something for me to put a little bit
more money in.
Um, so, that's certainly part of my
strategy is in this moment,
um, I've made a lot of money off of,
call it, the straightforward trade,
being technology, expose yourself to
equities. Uh, it's it's been great. Now,
I'm starting to take some of those wins
and I'm starting to diversify more, a
little bit into gold is one of the plays
that I'm making.
Um, going more broad into
>> I'm more worried, Tom, not about that,
which is the sensible way of owning
gold. Everyone should own a bit of gold.
It's the strategy of telling people that
this is all going to unravel in this big
world world order change.
And what happens is it psychologically
affects people that cost them a fortune.
>> Yeah, no, I think you got your finger on
something. I want to make sure that you
you realize I'm not saying that. So,
>> I know that the story you're telling is
and people won't hear what you've just
said, which is like, oh, I've got a
percentage of my allocation in gold
because it's got a place in a portfolio
and it feels right. I can see a trend
there,
which is very rational, logical, to the
US is doing this and this is a 4D jigsaw
puzzle of which the Chinese are going to
win cuz they're going to take over the
the rare earth metals in Africa and the
Belt and Road and the US can't see this
and you know, and then suddenly there's
going to be a new currency and it's
gold, but that whole stuff
gets people into a feeling that
it's all about to end.
Any day now,
my position in the US or the US economy
or US equities,
can't you see they're going to take it
away from us?
>> Well, let me let me ask you a very
direct question.
They're all selling.
Well, yeah, they're all selling clicks
and certainty and all that, totally
understand. But but let me ask you a
very specific question.
Because I have this belief that oh, this
is something that I think it's happening
in the background, I don't own any
long-term US debt. So, I own a ton of US
debt, but it's all short-term.
So, that's a very direct way that that
belief plays out in my portfolio. Do you
think that's crazy? And you own
long-term debt and you're like, "Yay."
Or
>> No, I I
I was a bond holder for years cuz it was
a
bond bull market. As we went, you know,
as the baby boomers went through
retirement, it drove down
um inflation. I still think
I don't think we're going to have long
inflation. I think we'll have deflation
back again cuz that's what population
shrinkage and technology does.
But, you might as well back the
innovation, which is owning the equity
than owning the bond, which is the US
government's liability. So, no, I
wouldn't I wouldn't own them. Short-term
debt, great. Interest rates are pretty
decent right now.
Um you know, gives you a bit of cash
balance. Not a problem. If the world,
you know, if the markets correct
sharply, you've got some cash in
short-term T-bills.
Fantastic. You can use them. They're all
super sensible, you know, to have a bit
of gold,
a pot of cash
earning some some some yield,
um
some technology equities, bit of crypto.
It's a very sensible portfolio.
>> We'll get right back to the show in a
second, but first, I want to talk about
the customers you're losing without ever
knowing it and why today's episode is
brought to you by Qual the business
phone system built so you never miss an
opportunity.
Most businesses track leads coming in.
It's very important, but very few track
the ones that slip through the cracks
after a dropped follow-up or a buried
voicemail. Qual fixes that. All your
calls, texts, and voicemails now live in
one place so your team has the full
history and nothing slips through the
cracks. Qualtrics is the number one
rated business phone system on G2 and
trusted by over 90,000 businesses.
Qualtrics built-in AI agent handles
after-hours calls, answers questions,
and books appointments so you never miss
a lead. When money is on the line,
always say hello with Qualtrics. Try
Qualtrics for free plus get 20% off your
first 6 months at Qualtrics.com/impact.
That's q
u o.com/impact.
There's a moment every entrepreneur
remembers for the rest of their lives.
The moment a stranger, someone who
doesn't know them, doesn't owe them
anything, buys their product for the
first time. That's the moment that
business stops being a dream and starts
being real. Shopify is what gets you
there. From day one, everything you need
is already built. Professional templates
and AI tools that make your storefront
look incredible instantly. There's no
coding, no designer required. You get
Shopify checkout, the best converting
checkout on the planet, so customers
actually follow through with their
purchase, and Sidekick, which is
Shopify's built-in AI assistant. It's
ready to answer every question that
comes up so nothing slows you down from
getting your sales.
We used Shopify when Impact Theory had a
merch store. Everything was so easy from
day one. My team loved how simple it
was, and honestly, I was jealous of
entrepreneurs who had that leg up that I
didn't have when I first started out.
So, start your free trial today at
shopify.com/impact.
Now, let's get back to the show. You
mentioned earlier the K-shaped economy,
it's going to keep going. Oh my god,
this is It's so funny talking to you is
like a fascinating mirror on myself.
So, I look at the K-shaped economy and
let's say the let's say Say doom now,
come on. Yes. So, well, so I actually
don't buy into doom because that would
assume that I can see the future
clearly, which I know I cannot. But,
um when I
>> You assume it's going to rain tomorrow.
>> No, but I own an umbrella and I keep it
by the door. That's probably the right
way to think about me.
Uh so that should I go out and see
raindrops on the street, I'm not like
where the [\h__\h] do I get an umbrella.
Um
but so I look at the K-shaped economy.
This is probably the thing that I think
the most about. This is the only reason
that I started researching the economy
in the first place was um I I
at the point that 2020 hit, I was still
only a few years out from having
thousands of employees. A thousand of
them had grown up very hard. And so
they're, you know, at the the wrong side
of the K. They're on the wrong side of
the K. So, that's what got me engaged in
all of this. Now, I see in the US the
rise of the DSA, which occupies a
I am emotionally triggered by the DSA,
so that already gets me invested in all
of this.
Um but do you see any
um
concerns about
doing economic things that will ensure
that the K remains a K or to you is that
a nothingburger and it will peter out on
its own?
>> Which, the K-shaped economy?
>> Yeah, cuz I I see growing tensions in
the US that will not resolve until the K
is closer to the middle.
>> I say it's going to get worse.
And so is the
>> And not not a big deal or it's going to
get worse in this country.
>> deal, but it's been happening for quite
a while, which is why the US has done
this in politics.
And the UK's done this and everyone has
done this, right? There's virtually
centrism has disappeared
from everywhere.
Um why? Because
one group want to blame one group and
one want to blame another, but as I
said, a lot of this is down to
demographics. Blame World War II if you
want to blame anybody.
Um and so this whole issue doesn't go
away.
And that fight has also been the fight
between capital and labor. That's always
been the balance of politics and
economies.
We're about to get something bigger,
which is
we're going to split between the
accelerationists and the
decelerationists. Those who want to
embrace the technology to give them the
superpowers of economic superpowers or
physical superpowers or mental
superpowers
versus the people who are going to go
suck their teeth and go
"No, you don't want to do that.
This is dangerous. This is terrifying.
You don't know what it's going to do.
We're going to lose our jobs." Right?
That is going to be the defining battle.
And then it will eventually morph into
who wants to give the AI robots rights,
economic rights.
Uh that's all coming.
So, we're going to be divided for a long
time. The issue is the printing of
currency to service the debts, to keep
everybody's livelihoods basically okay.
Costs the poor side of society
everything.
And
I don't know the answer cuz every side
has tried it.
They all see it.
If you're If you're in the US, if you're
a Republican, the center of the country,
screwed because of the K-shaped economy.
If you're a Democrat, city dwellers who
aren't rich, screwed because of this.
There's their voters.
Both have tried, both have been in
power, none of Nobody's resolved any of
this because it's They can't.
The answer would be stop printing
currency. Mhm. What does that do? That
collapses all the pension system.
Cuz the equity market.
Which way do you want it? Do you want a
5% You want to You want to 8%
debasement, which is the cost of the
put?
Or do you want an 80% haircut? You
choose.
That's That That is That is the game,
unfortunately. It's horrific.
Most people choose the 8% cost.
>> Mhm.
When you look at um as a macro investor,
and you're looking at historicals, uh do
you go okay, this all leads to Maggie
Thatcher or what do you think this leads
to? Is this French Revolution or Maggie
Thatcher?
>> The fourth turning.
What who do you think is going to be
running economies in 10 years time?
It's obviously going to be AI.
The decision-making changes wildly.
We're already seeing AI in every
company.
It's not fully on the board of many, but
it is on some. If I go to the Middle
East, which I go often, and go and see
the sovereign wealth funds, they've got
AI on their investment committees as a
person who votes.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
And they've got it in companies and
they've got it in government.
We all will cuz it's smarter and better
at decision-making, more level-headed,
and can see the picture better than we
can.
So in terms of optimal allocation of
resources, which is what this whole game
of humanity does,
it's better than us.
We're all using it for marketing
strategies or whatever it is. Why? Cuz
it's better.
It's faster, makes better decisions.
It sees with more depth and connects
more dots than most people do. It's not
as good as the greatest people on earth,
but it's bloody good at everything. In
fact, every single topic known to
humanity and every single mental skill
known to humanity,
it's up there
with the point zero zero one percent.
So of course it's going to be running
governments. So when we talk about this
in the future, do you think that Gen Z
are going to say, you know what, we
should, you know, have
the the the
Gen Xers or the whatever? No, they're
all going to say,
of course it makes more sense to use AI.
So, that's where I think it's going.
And that changes now. Is does AI come
good, AI come bad? You know, that's the
whole world of sci-fi and we're going to
find out. That's where we're going.
We'll find out is it good or bad? And my
guess is it was built on our
intelligence, it'll be both good and bad
like we are. But generally speaking,
it'll just keep moving forward in a way
that doesn't blow everything up. Cuz if
it removes us,
it removes the compute that makes it.
The messy compute. Humans have this very
weird compute because we do
all sorts of random things driven by
qualia. So, we create this very complex
compute. It doesn't do that. Machines
don't do that yet.
What do you think Neuralink is about?
It's the
it's the direct connection between
machine compute and human compute. Okay,
that's super interesting.
It's unlikely to get rid of us because
it can't do without us like we can't get
rid of the trees
that we talked about before, the
ecosystem
of intelligence that allowed for
humanity.
If we did that, if we destroyed the
ecosystem, the planet, nature, we die.
We're all built on each other.
>> anybody make that argument. Um
tell me more. It is not immediately
uh obvious to me that that would be
true.
>> So, we were talking before and it's a
longer conversation for another day, but
I built a
a thesis which I call the universal
code, which is even more grandiose than
the everything code.
Um and more heuristic, even though I
come from the acknowledgement is I don't
know
I'm no expert in physics, philosophy,
mathematics, any of this stuff, but I
stumbled into this whole big thesis.
Part of the thesis is
that intelligence
is that is that
things atoms, particles, all the
component parts eventually start
creating coherence
and networks.
And what it does, and I'm going to go
back to
firstly humans.
So, humans
we are hugely curious. We network with
each other.
We then start compressing all the
intelligence of everything around us.
That is what science is. People don't
think of it that way.
Science exists. I mean, these things
exist. We think of science as a
breakthrough. It's not. It's us figuring
something out that already exists.
We just didn't know the story, and then
we find the story.
So, we're compressing
all of the knowledge of the things that
were around us.
How do, you know, how does geology work?
How does biology work? How does physics
work? How does
all of this exists.
We're not making it. So, we're
compressing the intelligence of
everything around us cuz we're the
apex intelligence.
The
AI is just compressing human
intelligence, of which more intelligence
will come out.
And the whole process of the universe is
exactly that. It is forming coherence,
compress that creates intelligence over
time.
And that
eventually compresses and forms more cuz
the universe solves for
output of intelligence per unit of
energy.
So, we So, AI is not going to kill us by
definition
because we are part of it.
Like nature is part of us.
And the atom The water is part of the
trees.
I know this sounds woo-woo. It's not.
It's actually just physics and biology.
This is exactly how things work.
You can't kill it off. Take the water
from the planet, all the trees die. Take
the trees, all the humans die, and all
the animals die.
Take the humans away, all AI dies. It's
all the same thing. We are the same
thing. We're just nodes in a larger
consciousness.
And a larger
computing process.
>> How are you investing through what is
obviously the biggest technological
revolution in human history?
>> I have a framework which is that the
universe, markets, and everything we do
solves for output of intelligence per
unit of energy.
This is one of the reasons why
we've seen technology stocks just
outperform everything. And this is why
crypto, which is also part of the same
idea,
outperformed everything over time. So,
it's been for me that basis. I think
this is a super cycle. Listen,
>> the the technology is sort of the
ultimate thing that this has all been
aimed at, and therefore it can't get big
enough.
>> It can never get big enough. It just
keeps attracting more capital cuz it's
the highest use of that capital.
Um and it has the most output in terms
of returns, but also for humanity. You
know, the humanity scale of what is
happening right now. You know, people
don't realize I mean AI is easily the
greatest discovery humanity will ever
make because we've created
intelligence. We've put electricity
through silicon, through sand, and
created intelligence.
All intelligence in the past was putting
electricity through carbon.
Now, electricity through sand is a
million times faster.
So, the silicon substrate is a million
times faster than the than the
biological substrate.
>> Wow.
>> Which is why we can't compete, is which
why we feel so far behind all the time.
And that's creating
not Metcalfe's law, but Reed's law,
which is Metcalfe's law squared.
And it's the fastest adoption of
anything, not any technology.
Reed's law doesn't even even exist in
biology.
>> Okay, I knew we would eventually get to
to Reed's law. I did not expect it this
fast. So, let's lay um a marker for
people. So, one, um there's going to be
two visions that are going to compete in
this interview. So, mine will be
paranoia, historically grounded, um
nothing ever goes up forever, even if
only because humans panic and run for
the doors. You have debt mechanisms and
things to think about. We'll we'll
debate that when we get there. Then
you've got the um far more optimistic
view that you have, which is always sort
of where you and I are as archetypes in
this conversation, um that you said a
you can AI can never get big enough
because this is sort of the ultimate
expression of what the universe is
attempting to do. So, capital is going
to flow there because it is the right
place for capital to go. Okay, now
you've you're very famous for Metcalfe's
law, which is the power of networks. Um
so, they grow exponentially or the the
um
value of them grows exponentially.
Walk me through what a double
exponential actually means. Like, how do
I even wrap my head around that?
>> So,
if we think of the internet as
Metcalfe's law, the value of the
internet is basically the number of
people using it, the number of
connections that they have. And
formally, it's like the number of the
nodes in the network squared or
something like that.
But, it doesn't matter. It basically for
simple idea is
the more people in the network doing
valuable things, the more valuable the
network is. Makes total sense. Now, when
you build another system on top of
something already growing
at Metcalfe's law,
you can get this double exponential.
So, to put it in simple terms,
AI is basically a compression of every
single thing that exists on the
internet.
And more. You know, if you think about
AI, Tesla self-driving is everything it
sees in the streets, or Google will have
everything it sees on every video that's
ever been created on you You know,
there's a lot going into this, vast
amounts of data. What you're doing now
is you're compounding information,
running it through a silicon substrate,
which is faster than anything we've
seen. Um as silicon chips get better and
better, and which is why Nvidia is so
powerful and all of that stuff. And what
you end up with is a double exponential.
So, double exponentials are not natural.
Or they weren't natural.
They've never existed.
People talked about it as like Reddit
subthreads would be built on top of
Reddit, and they were
um Reed's law.
I don't believe that, but this is
provably so. So, provably so is
Anthropic's revenue scaling
is the fastest of any company in human
history by
an order of magnitude.
Now, they'll do a they'll do something
like a hundred billion in revenues this
year from 18 months ago of zero.
>> So crazy.
>> Then we look at OpenAI. So, before
OpenAI, another technology built on the
internet was cryptocurrencies and
blockchains.
They scaled faster than the internet
itself because they have this incentive
mechanism of of the network having
actual value that you can invest in.
So, that was the fastest adoption of any
technology the world's ever seen, and
anybody who's ever seen me on your show
have heard me say that a lot.
Then AI came out,
and it got to a hundred million users in
a week.
And now OpenAI has a billion users, and
Gemini has a billion users. I don't know
what Meta's got, maybe 300 million
users, maybe 500 million users,
even even nobody really thinks of Meta
really as having cracked it.
And then you've got Anthropic and
everybody else, and then the Chinese
labs. I mean, this is
stupid.
And we wonder why
we feel left behind, we don't understand
it, we can't keep on top of it. It's
because it's moving faster than we can
comprehend.
We have no way. Exponentials are hard
enough. Double exponentials are
impossible.
>> From a philosophical view of looking at
why AI is ultimately going to
be the substrate through which we engage
with our lives, whether that's a smart
refrigerator, a smart blender,
having it help me with my homework,
whatever. That you've answered that, I
think, very, very clear. Where my
paranoia comes in, and the reason that I
look at Buffett as he's backing away, I
don't not exiting entirely, but
certainly backing away saying,
I don't think that people are investing
in a sensible way,
that resonates with me because I look at
something like
>> Although, he just did add to his Google
position.
>> Yes, but he also just backed out of his
Apple position. He's sitting on more
what people refer to as cash,
you know, historic levels. And now, for
me, I just look very simply at the Cape
ratio. And when I see the average has
been 16 to 17 X, and we're now sitting
at 40 X, meaning the revenues that are
actually generated by, let's just round
it to the S&P 500, versus what people
value the S&P 500 at, have become
not a-historic, but we're reaching
historic highs that we haven't seen
since the dot-com bubble burst.
And I go, okay, I believe the
technology, I believe everything that
you've just said in terms of its
importance, its inevitability, all true.
>> Is it priced right?
>> Is it priced right? And right now, we've
already seen OpenAI plateau. So, if you
were just all in on Open AI, you're
probably going to get hurt unless you
start adjusting.
The same thing could happen to Anthropic
because yes, its revenues are growing at
an insane rate, but it's still burning
capital faster than it's generating the
revenue. And so I go, "Hey, despite the
inevitability, there are going to be
people that get hurt economically
as we repeat the historical pattern of
every revolutionary technology ends up
taking on debt to the point where it
wipes out the first round of investors,
and then it's the inheritance generation
of investors that actually make the
money."
>> So, there's a number of things within
that. Firstly, the Cape ratio, just
don't forget debasement.
Debasement is what moves E
moves the price. So, the PE ratio,
price goes up because of the debasement
of currency, and earnings grows with GDP
or, you know, in the case of Anthropic,
different, right? So, that's always
going to trend higher because we keep
debasing the currency. So, you need to
kind of think of that in your head and
adjust it cuz there's an
>> So, before you move on from that, so
we've got if that's true cuz the Cape
ratio is looking at a 10-year average.
So, are you saying that the moment that
we're in now is so different than the
10-year rolling average that it's
completely expected that we would no
longer be in the 16 to 17 range that we
have been for the last 100 years or so,
and now 40 is like the new normal?
>> Yeah, so what we have seen
since 2008
is a use, yeah, a printing of currency
in a very obvious way.
And the printing of currency has changed
valuations because
the price keeps rising, equities keep
going up, but the earnings are more
constant because that's not affected by
debasement.
That that mechanism is part of what
makes equities look expensive.
Ignoring all of that,
to go to your point is, you know, is it
dangerous now
or when will it be dangerous? I mean,
all investments are dangerous. They
always get the down cycle.
You always get the up cycle.
Having lived through '95 to 2000, we
ain't seen nothing yet.
Nothing.
Um
so I don't think in the basis of
collective insanity, we're there yet.
>> Okay, so sorry, just to really restate
that point. So,
uh hey Tom, I've lived through more
investing cycles than you, which is
obviously true.
I I am so recent to this game. So, um
I've seen way worse.
We're not near the sort of um just
completely detached, nonsensical
investing yet, but you also believe that
yeah, there's a likelihood that some
people who are doing something foolish
will get hurt. Is that true so far?
>> If that's not true, then there is no
risk in financial markets and you know,
of course it's true. It's always been
true.
The job that we have is where are we?
Where are we in that cycle, right?
>> Two questions in, I want an answer to
that.
And then what do you do to protect
yourself? Is it No, I'm just so good at
knowing where we're at, I never miss. Is
it I do my best to know where we're at,
but I have some other downside
protection. How do you How are you
thinking about that right now in this
moment?
>> See, I'm an old fish in all these
things. Like I'm with crypto, it's the
same thing. I look at the long-term
secular trend and understand that
markets go up and down within it,
and it doesn't phase me.
In fact, what I look for is when you do
have a correction in a long-term secular
trend, you buy more. Just look at the
charts of the Nasdaq since
1982, since the advent of the
um
computer, the desktop computer,
it has just been this. And everyone goes
sucks their teeth and goes, "Well,
2000." I mean, [\h__\h] it was just a
blip on the chart. The answer to 2001,
when it fell,
I don't know what the Nasdaq fell. Then
50, 60%?
Was to buy more. It's always been the
answer. We've had this discussion about
crypto and Bitcoin and everything else.
People forget it every time because
emotion gets in the way of what you're
trying to achieve. Now,
you know, those losses, it depends
whether you can take the volatility. And
if you can't, then invest less or worry
all day about the bearish story and try
and use your charts and try and figure
out the risk parameters and all of that.
It's much easier not to do any of that.
Just invest less.
And then have some money held back for
when it does fall and then go, "Amazing.
I can't you know, pop open a bottle of
champagne, buy some stocks and
you think, great, I've got a discount."
But people can't do that. But that's
what I've taught myself to do is
you know, be very happy like seeing
where crypto has been against its
long-term trend, let's say Bitcoin, it's
on that trend at two standard deviations
oversold, which is historically every
time a fantastic time to buy.
It's when nobody else wants to buy.
And so So, that's how I That's how I I
think about that.
But the point being is there are ways of
measuring this.
Nothing is perfect. So, you you're
looking at, okay, so the debt is an
issue.
So, then we break apart the debt and
look at it and say, "Okay, how indebted
are these hyperscalers?"
I think the technical answer would be
[\h__\h] all.
>> You're saying not at all?
>> 4% of their market cap in debt. It's
fuckle.
How much cash do they generate more than
God? I mean, these things generate huge
amounts of cash. So, they've gone cash
flow negative.
Oh my God, it's the end of the world.
The largest cash flow generating
machines on Earth have gone cash flow
negative to build what? Have they wasted
it on
wine and women and what drugs? No.
They've built enormous amounts of
compute.
And they've got the revenues to pay
almost any interest rate on the debt ad
infinitum cuz they're 4% of their market
cap in debt and a fraction of their cash
flows.
Now, there's a bunch of others. There's
CoreWeave, there's maybe Oracle, there's
a bunch There's a bunch of special
purpose vehicles. Could those blow up?
Yes.
So, let's run through an even bigger
scenario that somebody like you will
weigh on their mind.
What happens if
OpenAI screw it all up? They've got
trillions of dollars of obligations and
it all goes wrong.
What happens tomorrow?
Firstly, the US government steps in.
There is no way that they can allow the
US to slow down on the race for
intelligence because you've got another
nation also on the race for intelligence
and anybody who wins this
wins everything.
And so, in game theory, you can have no
winner.
And everybody has to go max all out.
But more importantly, it's the same with
the companies.
The moment OpenAI goes bust, let's say,
all of the compute
gets bought in seconds by the fastest
bidder.
But the US government can't allow that
either cuz imagine Google buys all of
the compute or whatever it is, all of
the compute licenses, everything.
If Google buys it all, then Google
becomes the most powerful company on
Earth and they have the monopoly cuz if
you double compute, it's proven, you're
basically accelerating exponentially the
rate of intelligence output.
So, it's actually very hard to have
massive economic damage. Yes, you'll
have a shock, but you don't have
anything long-lasting. It's the same
happened with the fiber optics. You
know, they all they all got written off,
but the debt levels were so much higher
back in 2001-2 in those companies.
They were insanely leveraged, which is
not there yet.
>> So, do you remember what the rough
number was?
>> I cannot remember right now, but they
were just they had, you know, huge
amounts of um
negative free cash flow. In fact, they
made no money. They had no cash flows.
Don't forget, they had zero cash flows
really at that point and it was all
CapEx. Okay, that's very different.
That was the building of the rail roads
was all CapEx
and no trains running. It's only when
the trains were running did you make
money, but you had to lay all the tracks
and everything else. This is very, very,
very different uh by who's doing it.
But again, will you have accidents on
the way? Of course, you have to because
capital must allocate to the most
efficient path and people who get it
wrong will get punished by markets,
people who make mistakes, absolutely.
So then, is this affected by the
business cycle? Classically, the
business cycle would
peter out as liquidity starts getting
withdrawn and the Fed raise rates.
Firstly, we know from 2000 2022, these
guys don't really care about the Fed
raising rates because they have more
cash than God and they sit on huge piles
of the stuff and it earns them interest.
It doesn't matter if the interest rate
goes up a few percent, doesn't really
matter.
Does matter to the rest of the economy,
but not into this race.
But also, more importantly,
the CapEx is the largest build out in
all human history that's happening now.
So again, we live in extraordinary times
that I keep using this the phrase in all
human history and they're all real and
they're happening now. Talk about
simulation. I mean, it's ridiculous. So
this is the largest cap capex event ever
and we barely started. Don't forget this
entire thing kicked off
3 years ago.
We haven't even built the data centers.
Sure, Elon can manage to get a data
center up and running in about 4 or 5
months or whatever it was, which was
preposterous.
But we're only at I mean, the capex
plans go out to about 2030.
That's what the numbers we're seeing
that that the numbers of spending. But
I think we're about 30% of where we
should be on the builds this year
because
the electricity permitting is so slow.
There's There's factors that are
throttling this build-out that makes it
quite hard to build excess capacity.
Um So they're struggling trying to get
as much of this build-out done as
possible.
Uh and so I don't really think that's an
issue, but the capex then comes online.
So every time you put capex online, you
increase your compute, which increases
you in the race, which allows you to
monetize it more.
So this dip in in uh free cash flow is
really an investment in
2 years' time.
>> Okay, so one story that I hear is that
um there aren't as many companies
clamoring for the compute uh as they
expected there to be. You've got
somebody like Elon who builds out that
colossal data center only to then rent
that um compute back out because he
can't justify with his own AI company.
And so people are like, "Hey, this is
really um about two companies
essentially eating up the compute that
we have now." And whatever story is
being spun that says we have this
infinite need for compute just isn't
born out by the fact um that you have
somebody like Elon who's just now
renting it back out. He's I think he had
a third company in there that I didn't
recognize the name of. Um but it it
isn't like there's 300 companies that
are going after the compute. This really
is a story right now of two dominant
players.
>> Well, cuz it's so expensive.
This is not an easy game to win or to
start. But Elon got there and he's done
pretty well with xAI. He had to build
the compute. He had to build those data
centers. But now he's built a bigger and
better one, which is why he can rent out
Colossus. Meta have so much data cuz
they've got this massive network of
information that they hold anyway that
they have compute. So, why not lease out
your compute for huge returns, 30% 35%
margins plus,
and earn money on that to fund your
build out of the next phase of this.
So, we're seeing that Google are doing
both sides of this equation as well.
They're building massive amounts of
compute, using massive amounts of
compute, and um leasing massive amounts
of compute out to others. Amazon doing
the same. So, everybody is using all of
this at full capacity. Everything is at
full capacity. You look at the price of
every single GPU, they're all going up.
Rental rates of GPUs, all of them are
going up.
So, what you've got here is we're in the
middle of Jevons paradox. It's the more
abundant you make all of this stuff, the
more demand there is for it. And the
demand curve has been
insane.
It's insane the demand curve. And
think about it. What is the demand for
intelligence?
It's infinite.
Cuz intelligence itself with the rise of
agents has its own demand for
intelligence. Cuz intelligence is
the only thing that keeps compounding
over time.
So,
all I'm saying is this is the fastest um
the secular trend of
Reed's Law,
you will have some bad allocation of
capital.
You'll have people screwing it up.
Um you will have periods of time where
the markets
get nervous about all of this,
but this is not going to be stopped, not
in the greatest race that's ever been,
which is the race for intelligence.
>> If some of the debt starts collapsing
and we start having a liquidity problem
because lenders start going, "Whoa, I
don't want any more exposure." Um it
feels to me like this could get fragile
pretty fast. And so, if that's true,
then the undergirding thing becomes,
"Yeah, Tom, that doesn't matter because
this is US v. China. The US will print
money until the cows come home if that's
what they have to do to make sure that
this industry keeps growing." Is Is that
what you see as the ultimate backstop,
or is there something else?
>> Well, that's one of the backstops. The
other backstop is anybody who's got cash
who can buy more compute will.
Uh people can't get their head around
this is a good of infinite demands.
We've increased We're about to increase
the TAM, the total addressable market of
the planet by all the agents we're
bringing in,
who want compute,
who are doing tasks that create compute.
So, it isn't unlike anything else we've
ever seen. Everything else was defined
by human demand.
This is not.
So, that's change That changes a lot of
the equation. The other thing, it is
observably wrong that
the increase in demand for Chinese
models has lowered
has made it more fragile for
Anthropic or OpenAI. Observably, their
margins have remained.
So, what we're seeing is the pie growing
is not a fixed pie.
That makes sense if this is the largest
good and Elon will talk about this, too.
The largest thing, the largest good you
we've ever produced is intelligence. So,
therefore, the pie is infinite. So, the
pie keeps growing. Now, is is there
periods of time where the pie
slows down? Yeah, most likely via
politics than anything else.
Um but the pie keeps growing.
And therefore, if if they can maintain
margin, will they maintain you know, 55%
margins?
Maybe not.
But all the hyperscaler are going up as
well. That's insane that the margins are
all going up across every player in
this. So, there's nobody losing margin
because the demand growth is so big.
Now, when you look at the debt, who's
got the debt?
Well, you know, there's a bunch of
Google debt that's now been placed with,
you know, pension system and stuff like
that. But what is the risk of Google not
paying the debt?
About as close to zero as possible.
At least for now until they get to
a much bigger numbers.
Um
Coreweave debts and a bunch of these
data center debts, yeah.
They'll nuke some of those in special
purpose vehicles that are probably
leveraged.
That's ugly. What happens to that if
somebody buys all the compute cheap and
the thing accelerates?
So, but so we can have the it can
disjoint. So, I'm not saying it can't.
But what happens is the speed of which
it recovers
is going to be really shocking for
people because the moment you have
distressed assets that produce more
intelligence at cheap prices, they snap
and intelligence grows faster. More
output, um more things we can do with
it, the easier it is to use, all of this
stuff.
>> Okay, it sounds to me like you're
betting on the industry or the
technology, depending on how you want to
say it, versus any one individual
player. Is that actually accurate?
>> Yeah, correct.
Correct. And then your idea is, okay,
where do you want to place bets within
this?
You know, you've got the playing field
of bets.
Where's risky? Where's not? Where's
interesting? Yeah. Interesting to me
might not right now might be
Oracle.
Never fade Larry Ellison is one rule in
life.
Right? The guy knows what he's doing.
You look at the share price of Oracle
since he started the company, it is
unreal.
So, has he has Larry lost his mind?
He's gone to see the dead. Or is he
acknowledging what I've just said is
spend the money as fast as you can now,
build out as much computer ahead of
everybody else, and you
have a massively growing margin
business.
That's what I think he's doing. The
market doesn't see it that way. So,
sure. Okay, maybe that's one way of
looking at it, which is the argument
that if they fall fast enough, you get
to some interesting opportunities.
You know, then we look at
um Amazon, which is a
very interesting example.
In fact, super rare example, maybe
outside of SpaceX and others.
Amazon is an example of the productivity
miracle
that is likely to happen to the economy.
So, Amazon is using robots.
And the Amazon human uh the Amazon robot
human ratio is nearly one for one now.
And in the next few years, there'll be
more robots than humans working at
Amazon. In fact, Amazon's hiring
has been flat, and their robot hiring
has just kept going up vertically.
They've got self-driving vehicles.
They'll have self-driving deliveries.
They've got drones. They've got every
element. They've been way in advance of
anybody else. They're running like the
greatest logistics company the world has
ever seen.
>> It's incredible.
>> Using the cutting-edge technologies that
they built themselves. That's basically
what the economy is going to do. And you
look at their margins,
they hold up really well, and in fact
increase over time.
Um because they get more efficient and
that's what the economy's likely to do
which means that for you and I, there's
more money around. Becomes more
profitable to do things. It's more
productive to be a human or to run a
business.
>> I want to drill into that cuz I think
that there's um a base assumption that
you have that may not be familiar to a
lot of people. My question is, will that
artificial intelligence be an economic
actor? Will it create surplus? If so,
how? And then how does it get the
dollars that it needs? Because when I
think about right now the way the
governments operate, they basically
intentionally inflate away innovation to
get more liquidity into the system. Do
you see the Fed as one example and Warsh
has talked about this, but do you see
the Fed going, "Okay, AI's going to be
deflationary because that intelligence
is going to innovate rapidly. There's
going to be more stuff for people to
buy. Uh therefore it'll have a natural
deflationary pressure cuz there'll be
more goods chasing the same number of
dollars. So I, Kevin Warsh, am going to
inject more dollars into the system to
basically keep up with that. And so now
through some mechanism, QE or whatever,
uh the there will just be more dollars
floating around in the system. The AI is
going to win some of those dollars
through its own economic activity and
like it just keeps growing that way or
do you see something completely
different than that?
>> No, I mean there's look, there's a lot
to unpack and this is where we get into
that idea of the economic singularity
when the whole economic structure of the
world changes.
Elon spoke about that with the interview
with the economist as well.
And it's something I've been writing
about for a long time.
Is you get to a point where productivity
increases
and it starts offsetting the debt
growth.
>> And are you thinking of that as
productivity increases per human or
productivity increases per
agent? Like what how are you running
that math?
>> That's a That's a great question and
that shift is something we'll we'll
we'll come on to.
So if GDP growth equals population
growth plus productivity growth plus
debt growth.
Right, population is
you know
if you look at the labor force labor
force participation rate, it's declining
over time. The rate of population growth
is declining in the US and most other
Western countries now. So humans are
shrinking
in the countries that have all of the
economic output and all of the wealth.
And they're going to get replaced by AI
and robots.
I mean I
employ lots of
agents to do stuff for me.
And I have to pay for their compute and
they in return they do economic activity
or activity for me, whatever it may be.
Okay, fine. So we're starting to see the
I mean that that's only been going for a
year, don't forget. This is how fast
this shit's moving at. So we're starting
to see agents everywhere. Elon's just
released a platform for agents,
everybody is it's it's literally
everywhere. It's all happening and now
there is more
um
bots and agents on the internet than
there are humans and that just keeps
going exponentially. Huge network
effects of these things.
And they use computes and they use
energy and you know, all of those things
and that gives humans jobs building data
centers and all of this stuff that we
>> can say.
Um but also we bring the robots into the
equation. So we're increasing
synthetic humans here.
And what is the And that's productivity
because these things are very
productive, they don't sleep, they cheap
to run, all of this stuff. So what does
it do? It creates crazy outcomes for
GDP.
If GDP is growing at 10% or 20%, which
is very possible
beyond 2030.
It's very possible to see that. It's
very hard to debase your currency that
you can create
inflation.
>> That sounds like a challenge.
>> It's a challenge, but you don't
you don't need to because debt as a
percentage of GDP goes down. This is
what they did in the 1950s. And you and
I have talked about this in the past. So
that was the financial repression of the
50s and so it's you don't need as much
to debase that so you can give it to the
people.
And it still won't be inflationary
because you can increase let's say from
call it 5% right now, 6% and it goes up
to 8%
but if they can take it up to 10%
you're increasing a massive amount of
money
and as you said
goods prices still fall. We can produce
so much stuff for nothing.
Everyone can produce software for
literally zero. $200 a month.
It's insane.
What we can do. And I built so many
things myself. I'm non-technical, never
programmed, never looked in my GitHub,
not looked a line of code ever in my
life
and I've built 20 products.
All of which I've rolled out to Real
Vision members, Global Macro Investor
members, things I've used myself. Uh
it's extraordinary. So it's now become
free.
So this you
this absolute abundance is what is
coming.
And we'll see it in medicines, we'll see
it in just every part of this
intelligence touches because its job is
to make everything cheaper, more
efficient.
That's what it does really well.
So I just don't see the bearish case of
this.
Will it replace jobs? Absolutely.
But there's plenty of other roles for
humans to do to make money from. And one
of the good things about all of this is
we're actually losing workers right now
because the labor force participation
rate is falling.
And it's you know, from from my um work
it just keeps falling because the birth
deaths rate if you're going into the
future gives you a, you know, a 60
18-year lead on it.
>> Mhm.
>> So, we've just got a complete collapse
of the labor force participation rate to
come.
And what we're going to do is keep
offsetting that for a while, and that's
good. So, the boomers retire
and the boomers die
and it gets replaced by increased number
of robots and stuff for a while. So,
it's not the shocking transition that
people think. It's a transition we need
if not the economy collapses.
>> There is a
a caveat in your speech that's doing a
lot of work, which is that we're going
to see GDP growth 2030 plus because
right now our GDP sucks ass and we've
already brought a ton of
um agents on now. So, it sounds like the
bet that you're making is that, "Look,
this is only 3 years old. For as good as
things have gotten now, they're just
going to get so much better. So, don't
be alarmed that you're not seeing it
yet."
>> go back to Amazon, Tom.
Amazon has been ahead of this whole
thing. It's like the US economy in 5
years' time, 10 years' time, five five
seven years' time.
That's what Amazon is. They use robots
more than humans.
>> Yep. Okay.
>> They are using drones to deliver stuff.
They're using self-driving electric
vehicles to move around.
So, they are
an extraordinary example of a company
that is gaining productivity.
So, it uses less workers for more
output.
And that chart has just hooked up
massively as Amazon started really
leaning into the technology side of
this.
So,
that whole hookup in in productivity of
Amazon, you know, how much output per
human employee has gone through the
roof. That is exactly what we're about
to go through and Amazon is showing us
the way, but people don't want to
believe it.
>> Um that is the economic engine becomes
you have artificial intelligence. It
will be an economic actor whether it's
because you're able to now have a
thousand employees that are all all
artificial employees doing a thing or
um the AI itself begins to be
self-directed and doing its thing. But
ultimately, we're going to have to have
a way to um get money into the system.
>> They don't need money into the system if
they can be economic actors.
So the first stage is that economic
actors for us. So let's say
I want to I mean I think Shopify
connected it. There's a whole bunch that
connected it so you can have your agent
go and buy stuff.
Mhm. We're seeing this scramble for
stable coins, right? Back into crypto
land.
Massive scramble for this stuff.
Uh
the guy who built Stripe is like
you don't understand all of the
transactions are going to be agents.
So agents can instantly transact on
behalf of you as an economic actor.
So when you launch your game, my agent
will pay you for its for access to the
game. My agent will play the game for me
and then I can take over when I'm when I
get to the the level I want to do all of
this, right? That's all happening. That
will absolutely happen without question.
So at first this directed economic
actors I've got many friends who've
given their AI agents autonomy
and said
here's a hundred dollars
come back and make me money.
Um and
some fail, some some work, but it's a
learning process.
And we're very early. Again, most of
these agents have been around the whole
agent ability for us to use an agent
about a year old.
Yes, in the frontier labs inside they've
had agents, but for the public, no,
didn't happen.
So they're going to be economic actors
directed by us then on their own.
Because networks over time form
coherence and these things are already
forming networks.
And we will see
eventually, and people aren't ready for
these kind of conversations, but these
things autonomously will do will act and
they need to be fed like humans do. What
do they eat? They eat electricity
and compute. So, they need these things
like we eat food and water. You know,
one is our life force and the others our
energy supply.
They have to do the same thing.
And so therefore economic payments have
to happen cuz if not, they die,
obviously.
>> Yeah, I get that. So, the part that I'm
missing is why you're saying that money
won't have to be put into the system.
So, here's why despite hearing all of
that, I'm still not
understanding
>> right? Velocity of money goes through
the roof because you can make micro
instant payments in everything. That's
the whole idea of the stable coin rails
and the crypto rails. Is what they're
allowing is velocity of money so money
can get reused multiple times. You
actually don't need as much money if
it's if there's velocity of money, if
it's not an inflationary environment.
So, that's one of the key things of
this. You don't need to inject money.
Money's not a fixed pie.
You create money by economic
opportunity.
>> You you well, sort of. So, you have
velocity of money, yep, sure, got it.
That's going to create GDP, but that's
not going to solve the problem of
how are we actually going to inflate the
debt away? So, one of the points you
made
>> need to inflate it away cuz GDP grows
fast enough. It becomes too small to
matter.
>> So, you're saying just by increasing
velocity of money
>> No, just by increasing growth of the
economy.
So, let's say
>> Well, so hold on. The growth of the
economy is a set of variables, one of
which is velocity of money. So, which
variable, if it isn't velocity of money,
are you talking about increasing?
>> It's productivity.
Productivity is the big one. You move
productivity from
You move productivity from 2%
to 5%, you completely change the game.
But productivity can go much higher than
that. We just never be able to do it
before, but this is a very different
situation. And again, we go back to the
'50s, after World War
II,
US debt to GDP was 100 and something
percent government debt to GDP.
>> Yep.
>> By the end of the '60s, it was like 15%?
>> Mhm.
>> And what they'd done is the economy was
growing really strong,
and they kept interest rates down,
and so what happened it was debt
costs and debt compounding ended up
growing less than GDP. That's what did
that.
>> Yeah, but am I crazy? We were basically
pulling money out of the rest of the
world. So, the US was winning by getting
other people to um buy into products
being made in the US. So, this is a a
story of the US winning not at the
expense of other people cuz they were
certainly
>> we had the the biggest two economic
miracles were not the US.
They were actually They were actually
Japan and Germany.
They were the economic miracles that
people have forgotten about that. But up
until about 2000, well, in Japan's case,
>> sorry, you're you're going to have to
define what you mean by economic miracle
because they were ultimately buying the
things that we were making.
>> No, they were making a No, they made the
things that the US bought with the money
that they made from make selling goods.
It's not a fixed pie. You keep thinking
everything's a fixed pie. It's not. So,
the US made goods that sold abroad.
Their consumers consume goods cuz they
had a massive baby boom.
>> Mhm.
>> We bought The US bought massive amounts
of Japanese goods, extraordinary amounts
of Japanese goods. So much Japanese
goods that the Japanese have run a
surplus entire history since World War
II. And they did the same to Germany who
run a surplus cuz everybody buys German
goods. So, here's a here's a symbiotic
relationship where the US makes money as
the dominant global force. They make
goods that other people buy. They run a
deficit. In return, they're buying
massive amounts of goods from
Japan and Germany and it all worked. And
everybody had an economic miracle.
Everybody reduced their debt load.
>> Help me update my mental model. So,
you're post-World War II, US is the
global manufacturing hub of the world.
Japan is going to come online, but
they're certainly not online in the
'50s. Uh
I don't know the timeline as well in
Germany, but I'm going to guess it's
something similar. So, we begin to um
flip the script and call it the '60s
where this begins to reverse and Japan
starts becoming the producer of goods.
They become the cheap labor, etc., etc.
But the period in which we start um
solving our debt problem is the '50s and
'60s. This is before Japan solves that
problem. But hold on, because I have to
get to something or I'm going to be
confused forever. Uh so, the the um
question for me is that if we are doing
financial repression very specifically
in the '50s, we are holding the yield
curve down, but the only reason that it
works is that yes, inflation is higher
than the yield that bonds are paying,
but the real economy is growing. Being a
worker in a factory in Michigan, your
rates are going up faster than we're
inflating. And so, that's because we're
making and selling, not because we're
buying. We have not become that economy
yet.
So, what I'm trying to figure out is,
okay, we have $40 trillion in debt. It's
growing. It's going to keep getting
bigger. We're going to run something
very similar now. Warsh is saying, I
think there's a lot of interpretation in
what I'm about to say and you'll correct
me where I go wrong, but Warsh is
saying, "Hey, the the productivity
miracle is going to be artificial
intelligence. It's going to through an
increase in productivity, it's going to
make everything cheaper, but dear um
human, I'm only going to let you capture
some of that. I'm going to pump money
into the system. I'm going to inflate
the money supply and this may be where I
go wrong, but this is my vision of him.
I'm going to inflate the money supply to
make sure that the politicians are
happy. They can keep giving things away
for free and I need to inflate the debt
away anyway.
And okay, period. So, you're saying,
"No, no, no. What he's talking about is
>> talking we're talking different time
horizons. Yes, I completely agree.
He will definitely do that cuz there's
no way of doing it in the interim. You
can't just turn productivity on like
that. It takes time.
We we'll start to see it pick up. Will
the GDP growth pick up massively? Not
yet. You know, maybe we peak out in this
cycle at 4% which is will be good, you
know, um
but it's later after 2030 where it
starts to matter less. So, Warsh's job
is exactly that. It's just keep the ship
afloat.
Try not to raise rates too much.
Try to give liquidity when it's
necessary.
Try and make sure you pay the interest
on the debt and that requires printing
money.
Try and free up regulation on these
um technology companies. Let them try
and innovate and move as fast as they
can.
Um that that's the game. It's exactly
what Greenspan did. Exactly.
In the in the late 90s. He basically
came in, cut rates once, twice, and did
nothing.
He did nothing and let productivity do
the rest. So, we even had headline CPI
was was high in the late 90s, but he
didn't flinch. He just said, "Well, core
CPI is not going up because this force
is deflationary and productivity is
picking up."
And Walsh
Trump, Bessen,
and Walsh have all referred to the
Greenspan period. That's the playbook.
Um so,
yes, you're right. He will do that,
which is why stocks keep going up, why
people the K-shaped economy continues,
because people can't buy a house and
they can't,
you know, get the assets that they want
and it's it's it's the same. That
doesn't change, not yet.
>> Okay. You You and I have talked about
this before, and I think you're pretty
famous for this at this point, but the
the idea of the everything code,
um
super shorthand, liquidity drives
everything. So, help me understand. I
think of liquidity as, and again, these
are gross roundings, but I think of
liquidity as being primarily driven by
debt, uh eurodollar debt being probably
the most important in terms of the
economic respiration of the world.
Um
and so, when I think about, okay, how do
we meet the liquidity needs of um the
increased economic activity that AI is
going to bring,
um I don't think of it as a fixed pie at
all, but I do think there is a very
critical difference between wealth and
money.
So, I've got wealth easy enough. Wealth
can sort of come and go in an instant,
doesn't matter. But when something has
to be translated into money,
there you can have some weird things
happen. And so,
I may just be confused, but I don't
think velocity of of money is the same
as increased liquidity. Am I crazy? Is
that the same phenomenon?
>> Yeah Yes and no. So, increased
liquidity, liquidity is just think of it
as the total supply of dollars in the
system.
>> Mhm.
>> Simple as that, right?
>> Yeah, so not influenced by how fast it
turns over.
>> No.
>> Okay.
>> That's liquidity. Doesn't matter how
fast it turns over. It could be stuck.
And in many cases it was stuck for a
long time in the banking system and
other places where they needed the
liquidity or in the foreign bond holders
uh the the
foreign dollar it debtors in Asia and
stuff like that. They suck in all of
this capital cuz they need to pay the
debt. They suck in the dollars, which is
why we keep printing more cuz the debt,
as you say. Velocity of money is how
fast it turns around. So I get my $10
and I go to your shop and give you $10
and you
quickly go across the road to to give it
to the greengrocers and buy, you know,
some fruit across the road and they take
it and go and put it in their gas.
Right, that's four people have used the
same dollar. That's velocity.
>> Yep.
>> So if there's velocity of money, it's
free to move around quickly and easily.
So it's it's a game of musical chairs
that's super fast.
If there's no velocity of money, then I
give you the $10 and you just put it in
your piggy bank and
don't do anything for 3 years.
Right, that that dollar cannot be used
again.
So velocity is a crucial concept. Now,
some people think velocity is
can be inflationary. It just depends on
all the other backdrops, but what you
want is an economy where money's moving
around super fast
and it's plentiful.
>> Brother, leave us with like one final.
So if I represent the doom side of the
equation, um if you had to condense
everything that you've been talking
about here cuz you've given us the
breadcrumbs, but put it together in
terms of how you're thinking through
this moment. You're jubilant. Uh it's
clear that none of the concerns have um
rattled you. So if you were going to
infect people with that optimism, how
would you put the pieces together?
>> I I think I should infect someone with
the optimism because, you know,
that's my opinion and I do my work and
it's not it can be right, can be wrong.
But this is the greatest time to be
alive. We are seeing the fastest
changing technology
to humanity
that
could ever exist.
This is something extraordinary and I
keep saying it, we're putting
electricity through sand and creating
intelligence that's a million times
faster
than than putting it through a brain,
which is carbon.
It's extraordinary.
And
of course, that's going to attract all
the capital in the world. It's the same
with blockchain technology. These
technologies are fundamental substrates
of the new world.
So, don't avoid investing in it
because it might be racy. It might be
something you don't understand. Maybe
there's some risk in it because you will
definitely miss out.
And the way to deal with that is what we
talked about before is how do you
construct a portfolio that allows you
to have your umbrella at the front door
or
be the person who jumps out in swimming
you know, in
swimming costume out the front door
every day expecting it to be hot and
sunny, right?
It's just construct a portfolio that
allows you to do that without blowing
up.
So, never get so scared that you don't
invest
or too cautious cuz you will never get
out of the cave.
You're [\h__\h] You are always in the
bottom of the cave. There's no way out.
And don't on the other side with the
sunny disposition, don't think I'm going
to use leverage to get there faster. Tom
and I talked about this. We talked about
it over crypto before it blew up, during
it blew up, everything. We kept
explaining to people, don't do this. And
then it doesn't matter and nobody can
take your crypto away from you, but they
do if you've got leverage. So, you don't
leverage into it. So, then it's just a
matter of where your own psychology is.
But, just step back from all of the
debates and all of the stuff and realize
what is going on.
We've got a single man who owns the
largest private communications network
on Earth, but it's in space and he sent
it there by designing the rockets
himself that come back down to Earth and
land. He has cars that drive you.
And most people haven't been in a Tesla
self-driving car, put in the address,
and chatted with your friend in the car
and not without even having to look at
the road, really. It's unbelievable.
And it's This is the worst it'll ever
be.
If you haven't tried building something
with Claude or ChatGPT,
something that's in your head, could be
a game, it could be a dashboard, it
could be your finances, it could be your
stock market portfolio,
and realize that you too can now program
anything
in minutes by just talking to it. I
don't even type anymore. I just use
WhisperFlow. I talk into it and I have
six Claudes open
doing six different things that hurts my
brain, not on the same I'm trying to fix
one thing over here, write an essay over
there, do some
all at the same time just by talking to
it with a microphone. Hey, can you do
this? Hey, what happens to that? Do I
need to fix this? What does this mean?
Like an orchestrator.
These are the times we're living in.
We're living in the most extraordinary
thing.
So, just embrace it
cuz it's not going to stop. Whatever you
say, whatever anybody does, however
people complain about it, it can't stop.
It won't stop. So, the best thing is
just to lean into it and say, "You know
what? We're going along for the ride."
And as you as we've talked about, Tom,
that doesn't mean you have to risk all
of your savings or anything else on it.
You just have to realize where we're
going and it's not going to stop.
>> I love it. Brother, always an absolute
pleasure. Where can people follow along
with you?
>> Um, you can either find me on X. Uh,
that's easy at Real Vision
or you go to my There's got a personal
website, Real Vision, r a o u l p a l.
Um,
.com. As simple as that.
Oh, by the way, Tom, the other thing
that's happening is I am In the next
couple of weeks, I will release out to
the wild my AI
in my voice, trained on all of my
content.
>> Let's go.
>> And everything I've done and all the
economics thesis and stuff, so you can
just bring my AI on and have a
conversation and it's in my voice.
>> That's dope. And that comes out when?
>> I mean, it's it's basically out now, but
I just need to do a few tweaks, so it'll
be realvision.ai.
Um, and um, it'll be out in a couple of
weeks. And it's free to free to use.
You can talk to me, ask me questions,
give me charts of the market. You can,
you know, give me give me your doom
theory and say pick it apart. It's all
It's It's there and it's wild. I've even
trained it on like wines that I like,
travel, music stuff. It's like It's It's
very cool.
>> Wow, it's wild. Well, I can't wait to
try it. I'll give it I'll give it some
doom and some charts and see what it
says.
>> Perfect. Good to see you, my friend.
>> Awesome, man. Same to you. Guys, if you
have not already, be sure to subscribe
and until next time, my friends, be
legendary. Take care. Peace.
>> If you like this conversation, check out
this episode to learn more.
>> I think America's gone too far in
privatizing everything. Election
campaigns are something that should be
funded 100% by government money and
private donations should be banned. Not
even possible.
Set it up in such a way that you
guarantee you can't buy your